Guide to the Alan Dugald McKillop papers, 1921-1972 MS 269
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Alan Dugald McKillop papers
1921-1972
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
McKillop, Alan Dugald
MS 269
5 Linear Feet (5 boxes)
Professional papers, manuscript notes and personal correspondence of Alan Dugald McKillop, Professor of English, Rice University. Included in the collection are: James Thomson letters (photocopies); Samuel Richardson letters (photocopies); Aaron Hill letters; typescripts of articles; reviews of McKillop's books; reviews by McKillop; offprints by McKillop, offprints of other authors (most autographed).
Biographical Note
Alan Dugald McKillop taught English at Rice University beginning in 1920, and retired in 1968 as Trustee Distinguished Professor of English. His interests included 18th century poetry and prose, and British novelist Samuel Richardson and poet James Thomson in particular.
Born May 24, 1892 in Lynn, Massachusetts to Scottish parents, McKillop attended Harvard University, graduating summa cum laude in 1913 with a B.A. in philosophy. He returned to Harvard and earned his Ph.D. in English in 1920, and arriving at Rice Institute, September, 1920, to begin what would be forty-nine years of service to the Rice community. McKillop was a member of the Texas Philosopical Society, the Texas Institute of Letters, the Houston Philosophical Society, and Phi Beta Kappa.
A long-time friend of the Fondren Library, McKillop was the founding editor of the Fondren Library's publication "The Flyleaf," and was responsible for developing many of the library's key collections, including the Axson Collection of 18th century British plays.
McKillop died in Houston on August 5, 1974.
Scope and Contents
Professional papers, manuscript notes and personal correspondence of Alan Dugald McKillop, Professor of English, Rice University. Included in the collection are: James Thomson letters (photocopies); Samuel Richardson letters (photocopies); Aaron Hill letters; typescripts of articles; reviews of McKillop's books; reviews by McKillop; offprints by McKillop, offprints of other authors (most autographed).
Access Restrictions
No access restrictions; this material is open for research. Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the Alan Dugald McKillop estate, 1976.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged in the following seven series:
Subseries A: James Thomson letters
Subseries B: Samuel Richardson letters
Subseries C: General Correspondence
General
Richardson Family letters separated and processed as MS 279.
Index Terms
Subjects
English literature -- Early modern, 1500-1700 -- History and criticism; English literature -- 18th century -- History and criticism; Universities and colleges
Document Types
clippings (information artifacts); typescripts; corrrespondence
Subjects (Persons)
McKillop, Alan Dugald; McKillop, Alan Dugald; Richardson, Samuel; Thomson, James
- Series I: Typescripts Notes
  - Typescripts, two versions; Vade Mecum (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Typescripts, two incomplete versions; The Diction of Thomson's Seasons (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Typescript; Thomson's Liberty (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Typescript; Lucretius and Thomson typescript (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Typescript thesis; The Spasmodic School in Victorian Poetry: Introduction Bibliography (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Typescript thesis; The Spasmodic School: Philip James Bailey I (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Typescript thesis; The Spasmodic School: Alexander Smith II (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Typescript thesis; The Spasmodic School: Sydney Dobell III (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Mimmeograph thesis; The Spasmodic School: Wm. E. Aytoun V (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Typescript and mimmeograph; The Spasmodic School as a Whole VI (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Typecripts and Notes; Proofs for The Early Masters of English Fiction (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Illustrations for The Early Masters of English Fiction (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Talks (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - [Robert] Burns (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Typescript and Notes; Sterne copy [manuscripts and notes] (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Proofs for Tristram Shandy; [transcriptions and notes]; Laurence Sterne (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Notes, novel, miscellaneous by A.D. McKillop (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - An Ode to Mr. Handel photocopy (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Photocopy of A Seasonable Examination; unidentified photocopies, 1735 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Typescript; review of Richard Brinsley Sheridan by Landré-Augier (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Typescript; The Publication of James Thomson's Poems, 1726-1730 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Typescript; Are Novels Social Documents? (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Typescript; The Gothic Setting in English Fiction, 1764-1790 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Typescript; The Early Masters of English Fiction; speech (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Typescript; Eighteenth Century Sentimentalism in Theory and Practice (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Typescript of Literary Forgers-New and Old speech (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Typescript; Sizing Up a Library (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Typescript; Two More Thomson Letters (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Mimmeograph Tristam Shandy seminar notes (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Series II: Correspondence
  - Subseries A: James Thomson letters
    Arrangement note
    arranged in folders 1-7 chronologically using listing provided by Professor McKillop; photocopies of originals and printed transcripts
    - Letters, photocopies; originals and transcripts; related to James Thomson, Aaron Hill, D. Mallet, S. Mendes, E. Young, Shenstone, Pope with Thomson endorsements. (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Photocopy of printed transcriptions; published 1751; James Thomson to Aaron Hill (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Photocopies, typscripts and microfilm; list of James Thomson's letters (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - David Mallet and other photocopies; James Thomson (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Letters; James Thomson (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Letters, photocopy; James Thomson (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Photocopy of letters and transcripts of letters by James Thomson; notes and correspondence by A.D. McKillop. (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Work sheets; James Thomson's Castle of Indolence (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Etchings, notes and manuscript; James Thomson portraits and notes (Box 1)
    - James Thomson: reprint proposal and catalogue of household furniture (photocopies) (Box 1)
    - Photocopy of 1727 original printing; James Thomson's A Poem Sacred to the Memory of Sir Issac Newton (Box 1)
  - Subseries B: Samuel Richardson Letters
    - Photocopies of letters written by and to Samuel Richardson (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Photocopy: letters written by and to Samuel Richardson (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Photocopy: letter from Samuel Richardson to his nephew published in "The Imperial Review" of August 1804 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Subseries C: General Correspondence
    - James Hervey to Dr. Stonehouse; August 22, 1747; original (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Photocopy; Aaron Hill; letters; photocopies of contemporary printed transcriptions (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Henry Hame [Hume?] letter; photocopy of original (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Alan Dugald McKillop bibliography (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Correspondence with Lois G. Morrison and accompanying photocopies of related to earl 1700s materials (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Preface to Mr. Pope; photocopies of correspondence and notes (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Personal correspondence including letters regarding publication; folder 1 of 2 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Personal correspondence including letters regarding publication; folder 2 of 2 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Correspondence: Rice University Lovett, Dowden (Box 1, Folder 52)
      General note
      This folder contains a letter letter of appointment from Edgar Odell Lovett as well as a personal letter from Lovett. The folder also contains a letter notifying A.D. McKillop of a fellowship and includes personal correspondence with Wilfred Dowden.
    - Miscellaneous correspondence with George Sherburn (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Correspondence regarding James Thomson (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Correspondence concerning Samuel Richardson (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - A.D. McKillop papers, original poems, clippings; additional articles by other authors (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Photocopy of 1747 original printing; "The Pleasures of Melancholy A Poem" (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Photocopies; London Journal 1726 (Box 1, Folder 58)
- Series III: Reviews, Offprints and related materials by A. D. McKillop
  - Assorted clippings including reviews by and about McKillop; notes and clips on Thomson (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Photocopies of August 20, 1773 edition of Maryland Baltimore Journal; 1761 London map; Hereford Cathedral map (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - International Association of University Professors of Englsh, 3rd Triennial Conference; Jesus College Cambridge; 20-25 August, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Reviews and offprints by A.D. McKillop (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Reviews of books by A.D. McKillop: newspaper and periodical (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Etching plates for illustrations (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Offprints by various authors, most autographed (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Series IV: Manuscript Notes for Lecture/Publication
  - Manuscript Notes for Lecture/Publication; William Blake (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Manuscript Notes for Lecture/Publication; Austen (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Manuscript Notes for Lecture/Publication; Fielding; folder 1 of 3 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Manuscript Notes for Lecture/Publication; Fielding; folder 2 of 3 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Manuscript Notes for Lecture/Publication; Fielding; folder 3 of 3 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Manuscript Notes for Lecture/Publication; Hogarth (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Manuscript Notes for Lecture/Publication; Topic unknown (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Manuscript Notes for Lecture/Publication; Addison-Steele Period (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Manuscript Notes for Lecture/Publication; William Collins (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Manuscript Notes for Lecture/Publication; Defoe (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Manuscript Notes for Lecture/Publication; Defoe, Addison, Steele (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Manuscript Notes for Lecture/Publication; Pope (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Manuscript Notes for Lecture/Publication; Richardson (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Manuscript Notes for Lecture/Publication; Photos and postcards (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Manuscript Notes for Lecture/Publication; Early 18th Century Criticism (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Manuscript Notes for Lecture/Publication; Gray (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Manuscript Notes for Lecture/Publication; Samuel Johnson (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Manuscript Notes for Lecture/Publication; Prose (second half of Johnson-Boswell (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Manuscript Notes for Lecture/Publication; Johnson and others (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Manuscript Notes for Lecture/Publication; Swift; 1 of 2 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Manuscript Notes for Lecture/Publication; Swift; 2 of 2 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Manuscript Notes for Lecture/Publication; Sterne (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Manuscript Notes for Lecture/Publication; Sterne and other authors (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Manuscript Notes for Lecture/Publication; Sterne unpublished letters (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Manuscript Notes for Lecture/Publication; Collins (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Manuscript Notes for Lecture/Publication; Assorted Subjects (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Manuscript Notes for Lecture/Publication; Scott (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Manuscript Notes for Lecture/Publication; Drama (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Manuscript Notes for Lecture/Publication; Thomson, Fielding, others (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Manuscript Notes for Lecture/Publication; Sheridan, Goldsmith, drama (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Manuscript Notes for Lecture/Publication; Smollett (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Manuscript Notes for Lecture/Publication; Edward Young (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Manuscript Notes for Lecture/Publication; Poetry 2nd half of century (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Manuscript Notes for Lecture/Publication; Philosophy/Aesthetics (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Manuscript Notes for Lecture/Publication; Restoration, Dryden, Columbia (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Manuscript Notes for Lecture/Publication; Restoration (other) (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Manuscript Notes for Lecture/Publication; Notes on assorted writers (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Manuscript Notes for Lecture/Publication; 18th century Descr-Didac poems (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Manuscript Notes for Lecture/Publication; Miscellaneous (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Manuscript Notes for Lecture/Publication; Notes on manuscript on 3-inch by 5-inch cards (Box 5)